上溯至宇宙初始 周遭还只是一片漆黑
In the beginning, there was darkness.
不知何时 忽地一声巨响
And then... Bang!
时间空间以及物质皆由此发端
Giving birth to an endless expanding existence
此后不断膨胀 延伸 永无止境
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在不断为我们解开
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking
蕴藏于这里的那些神秘莫测
the mysterious, the mind-blowing,
令人大开眼界 致命的秘密
the deadly secrets of a place we call
我们称这个地方为"宇宙"
the universe.
太阳系
The Solar System.
它是如何在星际混乱的湮没中形成的
How did it emerge from the oblivion of interstellar chaos?
我们是由气体和灰尘组成的
We are made of gas and dust.
今日太阳和行星中藏有它们的身世奇迷
Today the sun and planets hold fascinating clues to their origins
它们起源于一团极其微小而不可见的颗粒
in a haze of particles so small, they're virtually invisible.
我们过去的证据 就在我们周围
The evidence of our past is all around us.
然而 创造出太阳系的巨大力量
But are the titanic forces that created our Solar System
在整个宇宙中是常见的吗
common throughout the universe?
开普勒候选系统 952
还是我们是特殊的
Or are we unique?
我们的太阳系似乎是很特殊的
Our Solar System seems to be one of the oddballs.
宇宙也许有无数方式来创造恒星和行星
The universe may have countless strategies for crafting stars and planets,
但是仅有一法能够决定太阳系的形成
but only one could determine how the Solar System was made.
宇宙:太阳系的形成
太阳系约在46亿年前开始形成
It begins at a point in time nearly 4.6 billion years ago.
一大团气体云诡异地在
A giant cloud of gas and dust floats eerily
银河偏远的旁支漂浮
through a remote arm of the Milky Way,
其温度为零下四百余度
chilled to more than 400 degrees below zero.
当它独自在那儿
When it's sitting there all alone
这团分子云中 没什么会发生
nothing much is happening in a molecular cloud.
它的温度很低
The temperatures are very low.
那些粒子移动得非常缓慢
The particles are moving around very, very slowly.
几乎就是静止不动
It's just sitting there.
但若附近有一颗超新星 即爆炸的恒星
But if you have a nearby supernova, an exploding star,
它就会释放冲击波穿过这团分子云
it can send a shockwave through this molecular cloud...
从而触发了引力坍缩
triggering its gravitational collapse.
这种坍缩是长期过程中的第一步
That collapse is the first step in a long process
这个过程促使了现在太阳系的形成
that brings the place we now call the Solar System into existence.
0至7亿年
现在我们要跟随其最初7亿年的时间线
Our mission now will be to follow a timeline of the first 700 million years,
在这段时间内 太阳系形成并趋于稳定
the epoch in which the Solar System formed and stabilized.
我们先来看看如今的太阳和其行星
We start by looking at the Sun and its planets as they are today.
我们过去的证据 就在我们周围
The evidence of our past is all around us.
在内太阳系的四颗行星
The four planets in the inner part of the Solar System
由岩石和金属组成
are made of rock and metal,
而外太阳系的四颗行星
and the four planets in the outter part of the Solar System
则是巨大的气体星球
are these giant balls of gas.
很明显 太阳系的形成经历很多不同的过程
So clearly, different processes were at play,
这也表明了我们是如何走到这一步的
and that tells us something about how we got here.
我们所知情形和现在科学家相信发生的无异
We learn the story as scientists presently believe it happened,
它发生于太阳系诞生的伊始
from time zero, the very beginning of our Solar System.
零点
超新星爆炸不仅给这巨大的气体云团
The supernova explosion not only seeds the giant gas cloud
带来了铁和铀这类重元素
with heavy elements like iron and uranium,
爆炸带来的震动将这团云推向了未来
the jolt of the explosion gives the cloud a push into the future,
波前锋将云团的气体压缩成一种临界物质
as wave fronts compress the cloud's gases into a critical mass.
在引力作用下 这一团物质开始坍缩
That mass begins to collapse under the force of gravity,
该过程无法停止 急速并且不可逆转
and then it's unstoppable. It's rapid, it's irreversible.
就像过山车达到轨道顶端
It's like a roller coaster reaching the top of its track
然后急速冲下另一边一样
and speeding down the other side.
这个注定要成为太阳系的坍缩云团
The collapsing cloud destined to become our solar System
成为了一座混沌运动的主题公园
becomes a virtual theme park of chaotic motion.
像北仙乐园这样的游乐园很适合让人们
An amusement park like North Fairy Farm is a great place to people to come
体验那种早期太阳系形成时的运动现象
and experience a kind of a motion that happens in the early solar system.
有引力 碰撞 动力 推力
There's gravity. There's collisions, momentum, forces.
在早期太阳系里发生的所有作用
All of those interactions that took place in the early Solar system
都能在这里的不同游乐项目中体现出来
can be found here on all the different kinds of rides.
在迅速坍缩的云团中 相互作用更为激烈
Those interactions intensify in the rapidly collapsing cloud,
气体和灰尘密集形成致密区域
where gas and dust contracts into dense pockets.
每一片区域都是恒星的温床
Each will become the nursery of a star.
当巨大的分子云被触发并且开始坍缩
When the giant molecular cloud was triggered and started to collapse,
很多原恒星和很多太阳系
a lot of other protostars and a lot of other solar systems
也都同时诞生了
were formed at the same time.
所以太阳的周围其实有许多
So our Sun actually has a lot of brother and sister stars
兄弟姐妹恒星 他们也在那时诞生
that formed right around the same time as the Sun.
太阳系形成的第一阶段
The first stages of our Solar System's creation
并不特殊
are hardly unique.
如今我们看到同样的事情发生在猎户座星云
Today we witness the same thing happening in the Orion constellation,
一团巨大的分子云 延展数百光年
where a giant molecular cloud stretches hundreds of light years across.
其中 坍缩区域正在孕育年轻的星球群
In some places, collapsing pockets are now forming clusters of young stars,
它们照亮了周围的气体
which light up the surrounding gas.
游乐场中的环形运动
The circus of motions in the amusement park
巧妙地模拟了构成太阳系的
aptly parallels the movements of space matter
太空物质的运动
that comes together to make the Solar System.
这些运动中最基本的是圆周运动
The most basic of these motions is circular,
就像天空旋转木马
like a celestial carousel.
当前太阳系云团坍缩时
As the pre-solar cloud collapses,
我们开始注意到它的旋转
we begin to notice its rotation,
5万年
这个旋转其实从一开始就存在
a spin that's actually been there from the beginning.
整个星系都在旋转
The entire galaxy rotates.
星系中的所有物质都在旋转
Everything in the galaxy rotates.
每种物质相对于其它物质都在旋转
Everything is rotating with respect to everything else.
所以旋转是恒星坍缩物理学的重要部分
And so rotation is part and parcel to the physics of... of stellar collapse.
接下来发生的 就如同旋转的冰上选手
What happens next resembles a spinning ice skater.
当她收起胳膊 便旋转得更快
When she draws in her arms, she spins faster.
当引力将云团中的气体聚集
As gravity draws in the cloud's gas,
云团不仅仅旋转得更快
the cloud not only spins faster...
不可避免的 它形成了碟形
It inevitably flattens into a disc.
我们在地球上也能看到类似的过程
We can see a similar process at work on Earth.
在加州的乔·卡里亚蒂玻璃吹制工作室
In places like Joe Cariati's glass blowing workshop in California,
天文学家劳拉·丹利正在观察吹制过程
where astronomer Laura Danly is observing the action.
乔先取出一团红热的液态玻璃
Joe begins with a round blob of red-hot molten glass.
其实我们就是拿出一个圆形实体
We basically just are taking a solid mass that was round
然后旋转它
and spinning it.
它变得扁平是因为液体
It flattens because it's much easier for the fluid,
也就是液态玻璃
the fluid of this liquid glass,
更容易围绕着旋转轴坍缩
to collapse in the same axes along the axes of spinning
而不是抗拒旋转和角动量
rather than try to fight the spin
向中心聚集
or fight the angular momentum and move closer.
正如我们的太阳系 若行星在此形成
And just like in our Solar System, if there were planets forming in there,
它们会在同一个平面上
they'd all be in the same plane.
这就像是我们的太阳系原行星盘一样
It's just like the disc of our Solar System.
现在 它看起来是个椭圆 而非圆形
Now, it looks kind of elliptical. It's not circular.
我们认为太阳系的圆形的
We think of our own Solar System as being circular.
但是我记得你告诉过我 原因是一边偏重
But I think you told me it had to do with there being more mass on one side.
所以这也许有点像双子星的形成
So maybe it's kind of like an analog of a binary star forming,
也就是 质量大一点的一边
where you've got maybe extra mass on one side that's
会形成恒星或褐矮星 又或者
also going to form into a star or a brown dwarf or maybe a...
一颗非常重的 类似木星的行星
just a very massive Jupiter-like planet.
真想摸摸它 但估计是个坏主意
It's so tempting to touch it, but I imagine it's a bad idea.
不 我们不能碰它 真的不能碰
Oh, no, we can't do that. Yeah. We can't do that.
十万年
时间到十万年时
100 thousand years after it began,
将要变为太阳系的云气彻底塌缩
the cloud that would become our Solar System is almost entirely collapsed
云气中心被逐渐形成的原恒星照亮
and its center is glowing with the radiance of an emerging protostar.
原恒星是恒星最原始的状态
A protostar is the very early state as of becoming a star,
那时恒星仍在塌缩
when the star is still collapsing down
辐射到周围的能量正来自于
and the energy that is radiating out
那种引力坍缩
is coming from that gravitational collapse.
恒星仍将升温 因为其体积在缩小
It's still getting hotter because it's getting smaller.
恒星的形成过程
It's not doing the nuclear reactions
其核心阶段与核反应过程是不同的
like a star will be doing when it's in its main phase of being a star.
出现的原恒星开始吞噬
The emerging protostar begins gobbling up the disc of gas and dust
组成太阳星云的气体和灰尘
that makes up what's called the solar nebula.
大部分云气都变成了太阳的一部分
So much of it will end up in the Sun,
余下给行星 月球
then what's left over for the planets, moons,
星子 甚至我们身体的部分 非常少
asteroids, and even our own bodies is so meager,
就像宇宙的施舍一样
it's almost a cosmic afterthought.
我们住在一颗行星上
We happen to live on a planet,
所以行星的组成成分对我们很重要
so the stuff that went into making the planet is very important to us.
但这仅仅是整体的一小部分而已
But it was just a tiny part of the whole mix.
这个停车场很好地说明了这一部分有多渺小
This parking lot is a good way of showing how tiny.
在如今的太阳系中
When you look at the Solar System today,
太阳占了总质量的99.85%
the sun is 99.85% of the total mass.
在停车场里的500辆车之中
So compared with the 500 cars in this parking lot,
我的车就和所有剩给
my car is just about all that's left over
行星 星子 和月球的成分一样
for all the planets, asteroids, and moons.
至于分给地球的
And as for the earth itself, well,
就和这个备胎分量一样 仅此而已
that might be comparable to this spare tire, nothing bigger.
一百万年
一百万年之后
At 1 million years after time zero
太阳系对行星建构材料的分类
the Solar System's method for sorting out
已经很明确了
its planet building material is clear,
根据温度 它们分布在原行星盘的不同区域
they're separated by the different temperatures in the disc.
靠近原太阳的地方
Close to the protosun,
两千度的高温 蒸发了所有物质
temperatures above 2,000 degrees vaporize everything.
然而 在约八百万公里处 是岩石带
But about 5 million miles out lies the rock line,
岩石带
这里足够冷 让金属和矿物质固化
where it's cool enough for metals and minerals to turn solid.
更远的区域是冰雪带
Much farther out lies the snow line,
冰雪带
这儿最冷可达零下三百七十五度
where it's as much as 375 degrees below 0,
冷到能让水 甲烷和氨冷冻成冰
cold enough for water, methane, and ammonia to freeze into ices.
早期的太阳系 和做棉花糖相似
The early Solar System is a little bit like making cotton candy.
为了演示如何做棉花糖
And to show us how cotton candy is made,
我们请凯西·吴 来为我们做美味糖果
we have Kathy Woo here to make us a delicious treat.
首先 我们拿出砂糖
First we take the sugar crystals,
然后将它倒入加热器中
and we pour that into the heating element.
在这里 加热器处于中间
The heating element in this case is here in the center.
在太阳系中 当然 也就是非常热的
In the case of the Solar System, of course, it's that very hot
太阳 它居中 融化一切靠近它的东西
sun in the middle that is melting things that are too close to it.
发热的太阳
And as that, uh, that hot Sun heats up,
它开始融化它周围的东西
it starts to melt the stuff that's close to it.
出来了
Whoa, there it comes.
你可以看见 周围飞舞的是太阳星云
This is now the solar nebula you can see flying around here.
在里面 你其实看不到任何东西
On the inside, you actually don't see anything.
东西都在里面融化了
The inside, it's all molten.
而在较冷的外围
And as it gets to the cooler outside,
太阳星云开始凝结
the solar nebula starts to condense.
你能看到 它开始在温度较低的
And you can see it starting to solidify all over the outside
太阳系外围固化
of the Solar System, where it's cold.
你可以看到内部的都是气体
You get a line of gaseous stuff on the inside
外围的都是固体
and the solid stuff on the outside.
这与早期的原行星非常相似
This is also a very good analogy for what those early protoplanets are like.
它们开始互相粘结
They start to accrete by all sticking together,
非常像这些棉花糖
very much like this cotton candy does,
这些东西变得越来越大
and make larger and larger things
仅仅来自于这些小颗粒晶体 也就是
coming from these tiny little pieces of...of crystal that are
棉花糖中的糖
the sugar that's in the cotton candy.
- 谢谢 - 不客气
- Thank you. - You're welcome.
太阳系真好吃
The Solar System is delicious.
粘结在一起的微粒 现阶段还很微小
The particles sticking together are microscopic at this point,
远远小于融化的砂糖
far smaller than the melting sugar crystals.
棉花糖展示了太阳系中的颗粒如何粘结
And as cotton candy illustrates how these solids accrete in the solar System,
另一个游乐场项目表明了它们如何增大
another amusement park attraction shows what makes them grow.
碰碰车如果不碰撞的话 就不好玩了
Bumper cars wouldn't be much fun without collisions.
在太阳系中 没有碰撞
And in the Solar System, without collisions,
就没有成长和积累
there would be no growth, no accretion.
早期太阳系中发生的积累碰撞
The accretion collisions that were happening in the early solar System
碰撞使物体
are of the kind that allow objects to stick together
通过摩擦过程而得到粘结
through various kinds of essentially friction-type processes,
这些东西因为力学作用
where you have things getting stuck together
而结合在了一起
just due to mechanical interaction.
在内太阳系里
In the inner Solar System,
这是个耗时的过程
the process is time-consuming,
因为微小的宇宙尘粒形成缓慢
as tiny cosmic dust balls form slowly,
只能在围绕早期太阳的公转中
stuck together only by random collisions
通过随机碰撞得到粘结
in their orbits around the early Sun.
但在外太阳系 情况便大为不同了
But in the outer Solar System, the story is dramatically different.
巨大的星球就在弹指一挥间
The giant planets are about to burst into existence
突然地出现
in a cosmic blink of an eye.
从气体和灰尘构成的云团开始
Beginning as a cloud of gas and dust,
太阳系的形成需耗时七亿年之久
the making of our Solar System will take 700 million years.
现在 诞生两百万年之后
Now, just 2 million years after its birth,
两百万年
这个年轻的系统开始创造一个行星家族
the young system takes its first steps in creating a family of planets,
这个家族有朝一日会诞出木星 土星
that one day will be as diverse as Jupiter, Saturn...
和地球
or the Earth.
目前 它们还只是一堆堆的物质
For now though, they're just chunks of matter
仍在混乱的太阳星云中坐着过山车
continuing their rollercoaster ride in the turbulence of the solar nebula.
主要由氢气组成的旋转大原行星盘里
The thick rotating disc made mostly of hydrogen gas,
固体点缀其中
is embedded with solids.
内部区域充满了小石块
The inner zone is filled with small chunks of rock,
岩石带
但外围则是冰雪带
but outside the boundary known as the snow line,
这儿也有冻结的甲烷 氨和水
there are also ices of methane, ammonia, and water
冰雪带
它们主宰了原行星盘外圈 这是有原因的
which dominate the outer disc, and for good reason.
它们都是不同形态的氢化物
They're all hydrogen compounds of one form or another.
在那时的太阳系中
And hydrogen is the most abundant element
氢是最主要的元素
in the region of the Solar System at that point.
大量的氢和其它元素结合 比如
That abundant hydrogen is combining with elements such as
和氧气合成水 和碳合成甲烷
oxygen to form the water, or carbon to form the methane,
或者和氮合成氨 从而有了这些合成物
or nitrogen to form the ammonia, and giving us those compounds,
它们随后凝结成冰
which are then freezing out.
在扰动中不断的碰撞
Continual collisions amid the turbulence...
使微小的灰尘的冰粒
make tiny specks of dust and ice
由于摩擦产生静电荷而结合在一起
stick together through friction and static electricity
直至它们大到重力可以对它们产生影响
until they're large enough for gravity to take over.
最终它们形成星子
Eventually, they become planetesimals.
星子是太阳系形成的原始基础
Planetesimals were the original building box of our Solar System.
它们出奇的小
They're incredibly small,
直径大约在800到1600米
only about half a mile to a mile across,
但在早期的太阳系中有无数的星子
but there was countless numbers in the early Solar System,
它们到处都是
it was simply littered with them.
这些直径800米的星子
These half-mile planetesimals
最终将形成大行星 但却大小不一
will eventually form full-scale planets, but of distinctly different sizes.
这就是来自加州圣马特奥市的瑞安·陈
That's what Ryan Chan of San Mateo, California
想要对宇宙提出的问题
wanted to ask the universe by writing...
询问宇宙
为什么靠近太阳的行星要比远离太阳的大行星小
瑞安 内太阳系的行星要比外围的小
Ryan, the inner planets are smaller than the outter planets
因为内行星的组成原料不够充足
because the inner planets didn't have much material from which to be made.
只有金属 石头什么的
Just metals, and rocks and things like that.
但是外围的行星在形成一个类地的核心后
But outter planets, after forming an earthlike core,
可以吸收冰态的水 甲烷和二氧化碳
were able to attract ices of water, amonium, methane and carbon dioxide
这使它们变得更大
that made them get bigger,
同时它们的引力吸引气体从而越来越大
and then their gravitationally attracted gases, becoming much, much bigger.
询问宇宙
三百万年
诞生起点后的三百万年
3 million years after time zero,
星子合并为 更大的东西
planetesimals are merging into bigger objects
我们称之为行星胚胎或者原行星
called planet embryos or protoplanets.
原行星是由星子形成的
Protoplanets are built up of planetesimals,
因此它们更大 和月亮差不多大
so they're larger, about the size of our Moon.
在冰雪带之外 处处皆冰
Just beyond the snow line, where ice is most abundant,
随着大量原行星的碰撞和融合
the teeming mob of protoplanets collide and fuse
行星迅速形成
in a frenzy of planet-building.
只用了三百万年
Within just 3 million years,
这些碰撞便形成一颗冰冻的早期行星
these collisions give birth to a frozen young planet
而它注定成为太阳系中的巨头
destined to become the monster of the Solar System...
它就是早期的木星
The infant Jupiter.
在它成为巨大的行星之前
Before it became a giant planet,
木星就好像是一颗巨型地球
Jupiter was like a sort of super Earth.
质量是地球的十到十五倍
Maybe 10 or 15 Earth masses.
早期的木星由岩石和冰组成 并且不断增大
The early Jupiter is made of rock and ice and continues to grow.
在一个关键时刻
At a crucial moment,
最后一颗原行星撞到了木星表面
one last protoplanet slams into its surface.
对于太阳系的形成
It's another roller coaster like tipping point
这又是一次转折性的时刻
in the making of the Solar System.
增加的质量使木星突破临界点
The added mass sends Jupiter over the edge
变成一个引力强大的行星
to become a gravitational bully.
当它达到一个临界质量后
After it reached a certain critical mass,
木星的引力可以快速的吸引原料
Jupiter's gravity was able to very quickly draw in material,
类似失控效应 它迅速变大
sort of a runaway effect that made it very large very fast.
就像一台宇宙吸尘器
Like a cosmic vacuum cleaner,
木星吸引了在它运行轨道上的所有气体
Jupiter sweeps up virtually all the gas in its orbital path,
增至现在体积的90% 这只用了十万年
growing to 90% of its present size in just 100,000 years.
土星 海王星和天王星在木星之后
Saturn, Neptune, and Uranus in turn follow Jupiter
吞噬了足够的气体 变身为气体巨星
in devouring enough gas to become gas giants.
这种一颗或多颗行星的吞噬行为
The dramatic sweep of one or more planets
为恒星盘清理出了一条轨道
clearing a lane through a disc around a star
这种现象在宇宙中十分常见
is thought to be common in the universe,
最近一次观测发现证实了此现象
a fact borne out in recent telescope discoveries.
该过程在其他太阳系形成中也曾出现
We see this process happening in other solar systems being formed as well.
最终我们可以捕捉其他恒星周围的原行星盘
We're finally at the point where we can image other discs around stars
以及环绕它们的大行星
and the gaps that are being created by the large planets
所清理出的缺口
that are orbiting them.
11年初 天文学家用夏威夷的斯巴鲁望远镜
In early 2011, astronomers using the Subaru telescope in Hawaii
拍到了一张距地球450光年的恒星照片
released a photograph of a star 450 light years from earth.
先进的光学掩模使他们可以
An advanced optical mask allowed them
屏蔽掉恒星本身的光芒
to block out the light of the star itself,
显示出原行星盘首个直接图像
revealing the first direct image of a disc with zones
以及行星清理出的区域
cleared out by orbiting planets.
那是一张惊人的高分辨率照片
That's a really amazing high-resolution image
从它可已看出由气体和灰尘形成的原行星盘
that shows a disc of gas and dust around a star,
以及内层已被一颗或多颗行星吸附
and the inner parts have been carved out by one or more planets
作为原料
that have accreted material
同时将其它原料驱走
and also flung other material away.
经过三百万年时间
3 million years along the timeline,
木星和土星已经成为太阳系的巨头
Jupiter and Saturn are now the titans of the Solar System.
这两个巨头最终包含了
The two giant planets will eventually contain 92%
整个星系92%的非太阳质量
of all the non-solar mass in the entire system.
一千万年
在它形成的一千万年内
10 million years into its life,
年轻的太阳系几乎没有气体了
the young Solar System is virtually out of gas.
而正是是氢气和氦气
In this case the gas is the hydrogen and helium
造就了木星和土星的快速成长
that fueled Jupiter and Saturn's swift growth.
恒星形成过程中会释放超级太阳风
The forming star had this huge solar wind that was
将原料吹离太阳系
clearing material out of the Solar System.
木星和土星十分幸运
Jupiter and Saturn were fortunate enough
它们吞噬了轨道上吹散的大部分原料
to pick up most of this material in their orbits,
所以他们特别大
which is why they're so large.
天王星和海王星则不那么走运
Uranus and Neptune were a bit later to the game
他们没能得到那么多原料
and were unable to pick up as much material,
所以他们要比木星和土星小
which is why they're smaller than Jupiter and Saturn.
在灰尘和气体被吹走的这段时间
During the time before the dust and gas were blown away,
正在形成的太阳系在宇宙中深藏不露
the forming Solar System was largely hidden from the rest of the universe.
尽管灰尘和气体形成了行星
Even as dust and gas were forming planets,
但原行星盘还是足够厚
the disc remained thick enough
能阻档来自太阳系中心的元太阳光
to block light from the protosun at the center.
在数倍日地距离的地方
At a distance of several Earth distances from the Sun
假如你向太阳看
for example, looking towards the Sun
在太阳系早期
in the early phases of the Solar System,
我们看不见太阳
we wouldn't be able to see the Sun.
根本没有可见光
We wouldn't be able to see the visible light.
那么早期的太阳系在遥远的
What would the early Solar System have looked like
外星人的眼中是什么样的呢
to alien astronomers gazing at us from even greater distances?
哈勃望远镜为我们拍下了几张距离地球
The Hubble space telescope shows us with photos of protoplanetary discs
1350光年之遥的恒星原行星盘的照片
in a star-forming region 1,350 light years from Earth.
相对于我们的视线
We can see them at a variety of angles, tilts
我们能从许多角度看到它们
relative to our line of sight.
比如 若它是正面朝我们
For example, if they are face-on,
我们可以看到被星盘包围的一个中央恒星
we can see a central star surrounded by a disc.
但是当我们从侧面看时
But when we look at these objects edge-on,
气体和灰尘就会阻挡我们看恒星的视线
the gas and dust that is between our line of sight
使我们无法看到它的光芒
and the central star blocks the light of the star.
但现在 自太阳系开始形成一千万年后
But now, 10 million years after the Solar System began to form,
气体和灰尘几乎散尽
with the dust and gas virtually gone,
准太阳的光芒照耀着宇宙
the sun-to-be shines brilliantly through space.
这时它还未真正经历恒星的形成过程
It has yet to go through the process of becoming a true star,
它在现代人的眼中还很陌生
and at this point, it would seem strange to modern eyes.
光谱与现在有很大区别
The spectrum of light was very different.
它释放出巨大的能量 和现在一样
So it was putting out a lot of energy, just as it does today,
但是在它的光谱中红色光谱更多
but it was actually much redder in its spectrum.
因此早期的太阳系和今天相比
So that early Solar System would have been a very different color
颜色大为不同
from what we see today.
原恒星是橘黄色的
The protostar, orange-yellow in appearance,
温度极高 活动剧烈
is a seething cauldron.
在一些星系中
In some systems,
收缩云的中心只是闪烁着
the cores of contracting clouds never glow with anything more
棕矮星微弱的光芒
than the dim light of dull brown dwarfs.
我们早期的太阳现在面临一个关键时刻
Our early Sun now nears a critical point.
其炽热的内部是否会消散瓦解
Will its internal furnace sputter and fail,
还是会冲破核障碍
or will it breach the nuclear threshold
在广袤的星系中以真正的恒星之光闪耀
and shine across the galaxy with all the brilliance of a true star?
现在是太阳系形成过程中
We are now at the most critical point
至关重要的时刻
in the making of our Solar System.
太阳诞生五千万年后
At 50 million years old,
原太阳及其周围的行星年龄
the protosun and its forming planets
连现在的百分之一都不到
are barely 1% of their present age.
在诸多系统中
In many systems,
中央星没有有足够的质量使其全面燃烧
the central star doesn't have enough mass to fully ignite.
但是太阳却可以打破这一命运
But our Sun is about to overcome that fate.
它已到达热量和压力的临界点
It has reached the critical threshold of heat and pressure
因此其中心可以进行核聚变
where nuclear fusion can begin in its core.
借助与氢弹爆炸的同类能量
Using the same awesome energy that powers the hydrogen bomb,
太阳浴火而生 成为新生的完整恒星
our Sun bursts into life as a fully-formed newborn star.
从太阳系开始形成起
In about 50 million years into the life of the Solar System's,
的五千万年后
since it first began forming,
太阳进入了一个不同形成阶段
the Sun goes into a different phase,
不断燃烧氢气 进行核聚变
burning hydrogen, actually doing nuclear fusion.
那时太阳演变成了
At that point the sun becomes
我们现在所认为的完全意义上的恒星
what we think of as now a fully-fledged star.
太阳会随着核聚变不断向前发展
Nuclear fusion will carry the Sun into the distant future.
它会燃烧足够长的时间
It will burn long enough
以支撑地球上生命的进化
to support the evolution of life on Earth,
并将持续发光一百亿年
shining unceasingly for about 10 billion years.
与新生的太阳所不同
Unlike the newly nuclear Sun,
太阳系其他行星还未成形
the rest of the Solar System is far from mature.
四千万年前 冰雪带外冰冻的气体巨行星
40 million years earlier, the frozen gas giants outside the snow line
停止生长 达到其冰冻稳定期
ceased to grow and achieved an icy stability.
但在炽热的内太阳系
But in the hot inner solar system,
那里气体稀少 但充满岩石
where gas is rare but rocks abound,
依旧混乱不堪
chaos still reigns.
当太阳成为真正意义上的恒星时
By the time that the Sun has become a full-fledges star
太阳系内部的其他行星
the planets in the inner part of the Solar System
还处于形成过程中
are still trying to grow,
有些小型原行星聚齐在一起
there are small little protoplanets that are building together,
相互碰撞 逐渐变大
colliding, getting larger and larger,
最终形成太阳系中的
eventually to become those four big planets
四大行星
that we have in the inner Solar System.
在木星轨道内的一片狭小区域中
But just inside the orbit of Jupiter lies a narrow region
星子数量繁多
where the smaller planetesimals rule
而原行星则极其稀少
and protoplanets are rare.
这便是星子带 木星对其进行干扰
This is the asteroid belt, where Jupiter stirs things up
阻止了行星的形成
to prevent any planets from forming.
木星是最大的行星 它产生的重力影响
Jupiter is the largest planet so its gravitational influence
是太阳系中最大的
is the greatest in the Solar System.
在太阳系形成初期的一个时期
There was a point in the early Solar System
木星穿过了现在称为星子带的地方
where Jupiter was passing through what's now the asteroid belt,
加快了那里星子的运行速度
pumping up the velocities of the planetesimals there,
使它们相互间发生了毁灭性的碰撞
causing them to collide in a destructive manner.
然后它们就瓦解了
They blew apart.
我们试着模拟星子带中
We're gonna try to get a feel for what a destructive collision
所发生的毁灭性碰撞
is like in the asteroid belt.
但不能用真正的石头 因为它们太硬
But we can't use real rocks because they're too hard
而且我们能提供的速度很小
and the velocities available to us are too slow,
所以我们要做的是
so what we're going to do
使用这些特制的轻质石头
is use these special lightweight rocks,
这些是由特效师瑞安·强森制作的
which were made for us by Ryan Johnson, a special effects artist.
瑞安 你能介绍一下
Ryan, can you tell us about
这些特制的星子模型吗
these special lightweight simulated asteroids?
没问题
Sure.
我们使用的这些模型
So these props that we've developed here
是类似泡沫塑料的东西 在电影中
are a foamed plaster-type material that we use to
用来充当真正的石头
simulate real rocks in movies and films and things like that.
当我们想要打碎一些坚硬的东西时
Whenever we want something to break that looks like it's hard,
这种东西很容易就能碎掉 能变得粉碎
this stuff breaks really easy, and it crumbles.
所以我们要用这种材料
So what we've done is we've taken this same material,
制造一个更大的模型
and we've developed a much larger one
来模拟星子
we're gonna use to simulate an asteroid.
这里有两个
So we've got two of these,
我们要把他们狠狠地杂碎
and we'll smash 'em together really hard,
希望能模拟出星子碰撞的效果
and that'll hopefully simulate the collision of an asteroid.
你觉得我们应该用多大速度
So what sort of speed do you think we need
才能让它们撞碎
to smash them together so they'll break?
只需要其中一个从适合的高度落下
We just need to drop one on top of another
砸向另一个 这么高就行
from a reasonable height, and, uh... Something like that.
好吧 来试试
Okay, let's try it.
把线锤放下来
Looks, drop the cone
降落高度有5.5米
The distance of the drop is about 18 feet,
可以使降落星子模型的速度
which will give the falling asteroid a speed
达到每小时60公里
of 37 miles per hour.
再向下一点
Little bit more.
很好 很好 就在这里
Perfect. Perfect, right there.
好了 瑞安 我准备好了
Okay, Ryan, I'm ready for the drop.
好的 风有些大
Okay, it's pretty windy,
我们看看效果如何
but we'll see how we do.
很好 非常棒
All right! That is excellent.
- 我觉得很成功 - 谢谢
- I would say that's a success. - Oh, thanks.
- 很不错 - 是啊
- Yeah, that looks good. - Yep.
真奇妙 它们都分散开了
That's amazing, how much it's, like, really spread out.
没错 在星子带 这些碎块会
Right, so in the asteroid belt, all these pieces would
因引力作用重新聚合 形成瓦砾堆
gravitate back together and form a rubble pile,
就是现在所说的星子
what we would call an asteroid today.
如果它们一直向一处聚集
So if they're starting to come together all the time,
是不是就同行星形成过程一样
isn't that the same process that actually forms a planet?
那为什么行星不是这样形成的呢
Why wouldn't the planet form in that case?
不是的 在那时
Well, no, because then
这些星子一次又一次地遭到撞击
this thing gets hit again and again and again.
受此影响 它们会保持碎裂的状态
So these things keep getting pulverized by impacts,
只剩下一些小型的独立的瓦砾堆
and you're just left with little individual rubble piles,
而不是完整的行星
rather than a complete planet.
那这有没有模拟出
Does this reasonably replicate
你所认为的星子碰撞的样子呢
what you think possibly an asteroid collision would be?
这个模拟效果很成功 事实上
This is a pretty good analogy, in fact,
碰撞会产生大碎块 也会有细小粉末
because you get large pieces, you get dust.
所以我们认为的星子基本上是
And so what we think are asteroids are basically rubble piles
由大的碎块聚集而成的瓦砾堆
composed of these large pieces put together,
并覆盖在粉尘之中
covered then in dust.
所以我觉得你做的很不错
And, uh, and so yeah, I think you did a good job.
这就像是星子刚诞生的样子
This looks like a... Like a... The beginnings of an asteroid.
- 太好了 真高兴成功了 - 没错
- Great. Well, I'm glad it worked. - Right.
在现在的太阳系中并不是只有
The asteroid belt isn't the only region
星子带中无法形成真正的行星
in the emerging Solar System where planets fail to form.
在太阳系的外缘
At the outer fringes of the Solar System,
另一个小型物体构成的环带正静静运行着
another ring of small objects orbits in frozen silence...
柯伊伯带
The Kuiper belt.
柯伊伯带位于海王星轨道之上和之外
The Kuiper belt is a region at and beyond the orbit of Neptune
由岩石和冰体组成
that has a whole bunch of rocky and icy objects.
各物体之间相隔很远
Pretty far away from one another.
它们永远无法聚集而成一个行星
Now, they were never able to coalesce to form a planet
因为它们彼此间距离太远
because there's just not enough of them close enough together.
太阳系诞生后的五千万年
50 million years after the Solar System was born,
柯伊伯带和星子带中的物体
both the Kuiper and the asteroid belts have 100 times
是它们现在所含物体的一百多倍
more objects in them than they do today.
对于包括地球在内的岩石内行星的最终演化
These objects will play a monumentally destructive but vital role
这些物体扮演着极具破坏性却又至关重要的角色
in the final evolution of the rocky inner planets, including the Earth.
七千五百万年
内行星的形成时间
The inner planets take as much as 10 times longer
比冰雪带外的巨行星长十倍
to form than the giant planets outside the snow line.
七千五百万年后 这个过程接近完成
After 75 million years, the process is near completion.
距离年轻的太阳约1.5亿公里处
About 93 million miles from the young Sun,
原始地球已达行星大小并处于较稳定轨道上
the proto-Earth has reached planet size in a relatively stable orbit.
但是它有个伴行者
But it has a cosmic stalker.
确切来说认为早期的地球
It's actually believed that the Earth was, in its early phase,
有另一颗原行星相伴 名为忒伊亚
accompanied by another planet, a protoplanet called Theia,
的确跟地球的轨道相似
which was actually in a similar orbit to Earth,
大致遵循同一路径
essentially following roughly the same path.
这对姐妹星以危险的双生形式
For millions of years, the sister planets
围绕太阳互相追逐了几百万年
chase each other around the Sun in a dangerous duet.
但是即将来到的碰撞
But a clash is coming
将对地球的命运产生巨大的影响
that will have immense consequences for the fate of the Earth.
八千万年前巨大气云的塌缩
The making of our Solar System has gone on for 80 million years,
八千万年
我们太阳系才得以形成
since the collapse of the giant gas cloud that started the process.
内行星已经基本成型
The inner planets have largely taken shape,
但是即将孕育生命的地球
but now the Earth, which will one day harbor life,
现正面临夭折和巨变的危险
faces the potential of an early and cataclysmic death.
数百万年来
For millions of years,
原行星忒伊亚一直伴地球左右
Earth has been followed by the protoplanet Theia.
两颗星球基本在同一轨道运行
The two bodies travel in essentially the same orbit,
渐行渐近
gradually coming closer and closer.
现在 地球和忒伊亚碰撞一触即发
Now, for Earth and Theia, it's crunch time.
地球忒伊亚的碰撞在太阳系形成早期
The Earth-Theia collision early in the history
一定是件惊人的大事
of the Solar System must have been a spectacular event.
一个火星大小的物体撞入地球侧面
A Mars-sized object came in and hit Earth side
二者的部分地壳和地幔飞溅入太空
splattering part of the crust and mantle of both objects into space,
形成了一个碎片环 月球从此形成
forming a ring of debris from which the moon then formed.
地球在大灾变中幸存
Having survived the cataclysm
并得到了一个月球
and gained a moon,
作为内太阳系最稳定的行星之一
the Earth settles in as one of the stable planets
地球得以安顿下来
of the inner Solar System.
现在我们再来看看气态巨星
The drama now moves back to the gas giants,
它那变换的轨道令太阳系有崩离的危险
whose shifting orbits threaten to tear the Solar System apart.
五亿年
五亿年时
At 500 million years old,
太阳系的所有行星都形成了
all of the Solar System's planets have been formed.
但是在行星盘中围绕着碎片
But surrounded by debris in the planetary disc,
它们也在活动
they are on the move.
随着原行星盘中密度纹的形成
As waves of density formed in the disc
行星们几乎就在行星盘的实体纹中冲浪
the planets were almost surfing on the waves of material in the disc itself.
从行星们形成的地方
You're really shuffling the deck completely
到你最终见到它们的位置大相近庭
from where planets are formed to where we finally see them.
早期的太阳系 最远的三颗行星
In the early Solar System, the three outermost planets,
整体比它们今天离太阳近得多
as a group, are closer to the Sun than they are today.
海王星的原始轨道位于天王星内侧
And Neptune's original orbit is inside that of Uranus,
与它们当前的位置相反
the reverse of their current position.
另外 星子带和库伯带包含的物质
In addition, the asteroid and kuiper belts each
比它们今天要多一百倍
have 100 times more material than they do today.
这两个小区域不断地被巨行星
The small bodies of both belts are constantly flung around
及其强烈的引力甩动
by the giant planets and their intense gravity.
大行星虽然巨大
As massive as they are, the big planets react
但每次作用于某个星子时仍有反作用
every time they toss a planetesimal somewhere else.
反作用也许很小 但叠加起来
The reactions may be small, but they add up to
使巨行星的轨道定期转移到新的位置
make the orbits of the giant planets migrate to new positions.
早期 外行星倾向于环绕而行
Early on, the outer planets tended to move around quite a bit.
它们移动了
They migrated.
现在 土星 天王星和海王星
Now, Saturn, Uranus, and Neptune
将星子送往太阳
sent planetesimals in toward the Sun.
那意味着它们不得不慢慢向外移动
That means they had to generally move outwards,
而木星将星子远远地向外抛出
whereas Jupiter flung planetesimals out to very great distances,
甚至抛出太阳系
even ejected them from the Solar System,
那意味着木星不得不往里面移
and that means that Jupiter had to move in.
什么决定了位置的变换
What determines these in and out movements?
基于物理能量守恒定律
They result from a law of physics that says energy is never lost.
当一颗行星弹出一颗星子
When a planet ejects a planetesimal,
行星本身就往里移动一点
the planet itself has to move in a little bit,
那就是简单的能量交换
and that's simple conservation of energy.
它给了星子大量的能量
It's giving a lot of energy to the planetesimal,
将它倾倒出去
dumping it way out there.
那就是说 行星必须向内移动
That means it, the planet, has to move in.
它失去了能量
It loses energy.
如果一个轨道运行的物体失去能量
If an orbiting object loses energy,
它的移动速度就会下降
it's not moving as quickly.
就是说它降入近一点的轨道
That means it drops to a lower orbit.
这个游乐园再现了这种力的作用
The amusement park again illustrates the forces at work...
这就是弹弓作用
in this case, the slingshot effect.
它是大行星用以推动小物体的一种引力
It's a gravitational boost that large planets can give small objects.
在二十世纪七十年代 科学家们
In the 1970s, scientists exploited it
将引力开发应用于旅行者号太空船
to accelerate the Voyager spacecraft
使其行能走于太阳系外的行星间
as it swung from planet to planet in the outer Solar System.
在地球上 我们可以
Here on Earth we can think of
将处于边缘的过山车看作弹弓
the slingshot as a roller coaster over the edge.
我们在这里控制的穿梭过山车
The boomerang roller coaster ride that we have here
很好地例证了弹弓效应的力
is a nice example of the forces that are involved in the slingshot effect.
在地球上 地球引力是作用力
The gravity here makes this work here on Earth, using Earth's gravity.
重力把车沿着斜坡拉下来
It pulls down on the cart and it pulls down the slope,
然后车又回到斜坡上
and then the cart goes back up the slope
在沿坡而下的过程中获得了能量
due to the momentum it gained from coming down the slope.
如果我们把木星加入这个系统会怎么样呢
What if we were to add Jupiter to the system?
现在 木星的引力一直在把目标往里拉
Now, Jupiter's gravity will still pull the object in,
但木星使它围绕自己旋转
but Jupiter swings it around the planet,
它围着木星转了一圈
and it goes around Jupiter.
木星的动作给了它一个额外的反冲
And the motion of Jupiter gives it an extra kick
所以它得到了比初始更多的动力
so that it gets more momentum than it came in with
弹回到斜坡上 冲入太空
and gets shooting back up the slope and out into space.
七亿年
超过五亿年间 数百万小引力
Millions of small gravitational tugs have made subtle changes
使行星轨道产生了微妙的变化
to the planetary orbits for more than half a billion years.
地球和其他年轻的行星
Earth and the other young planets
能够处于有利于产生早期生命的环境
may settle into conditions conducive to early life.
要是这样 当气态巨星木星和土星
If so, it's about to be wiped out as the gas giants,
达到惊人的共振临界点 它就将毁灭了
Jupiter and Saturn, reach a remarkable tipping point called a resonance.
一旦木星和土星达到共振是很惨烈的
As soon as Jupiter and saturn hit the resonance it was catastrophic.
整个太阳系将在一百万年内被崩离
The entire Solar System flew apart in just a million years,
相对于太阳系的年纪 这是很短的时间
which is a tiny amount of time, compared to the age of the Solar System.
共振意味着土星每绕太阳一周
The resonance means that every time Saturn orbits the Sun once,
木星就会绕两周
Jupiter will go around twice.
结果是在太阳系的同一位置
The result, Jupiter and Saturn come very close to each other
木星和土星有规律地越靠越近
in the same part of the Solar System on a regular,
在不断进行的基础上产生巨大的引力泵
ongoing basis, creating an immense gravity pump.
就像给一个小孩荡秋千
It's like pumping a kid on a swing.
如果小孩荡秋千时 你推的时候恰到好处
If you hit the kid on the swing at just the right time,
你就可以让它越荡越高
you can get the motion to go higher and higher and higher.
最巨大的影响 是对两颗最远的巨行星
The most dramatic effect is on the two outermost giant planets.
所有行星都围绕太阳系旋转的时候
As all of the planets were orbiting around the Solar System,
彼此引力相互作用
having gravitational interactions with each other,
发生的最惊人事件之一 是天王星
one of the most amazing things that happened is that Uranus and
与海王星对调了位置
Neptune actually switched places.
这就是为什么现在海王星在天王星的外侧
So now Neptune is farther away than Uranus.
这种共振现象会引发灾难
The resonance is a cataclysm
而这灾难的影响会以迅雷不及掩耳之势
whose effects sweep through the system
波及整个太阳系 它不仅会使行星换位
at astounding speed, not only shifting orbits,
而且还会驱赶走太阳系中的大部分小星体
but clearing out most of the system's small objects.
单单是木星自身强大的吸引力
Jupiter alone is quite a gravitational bully
就足以慢慢削减星子带中星体的数量
and gradually depleted the asteroid belt.
而木星与土星共同造就的共振现象
But the Jupiter-Saturn resonance
则造成了星子带与库伯带中的星体急剧减少
caused a catastrophic depletion of both the asteroid belt and the Kuiper belt.
星子带与库伯带中99%的星体
99% of the bodies in the asteroid and kuiper belts
都被驱逐出了太阳系
are cleared.
但尽管这绝大多数星体都被驱逐出去了
While most of them are thrown out of the system,
有一小部分星体却冲向了木星的轨道内侧
some of them plunge inward.
由于太阳引力的吸引
Drawn by the gravity of the Sun,
它们穿越宇宙 直冲向内太阳系
they rip through space toward the inner Solar System.
内太阳系中的行星 如何才能逃脱劫难
How will the inner planets, including the Earth, escape the onslaught?
一团巨大的星云开始其塌缩过程之后7亿年
The making of our Solar System reaches a violent climax
太阳系的诞生历程达到了其壮丽的高潮
700 million years after the presolar cloud first began to collapse.
而地球则处于火线之上
And Earth is in the firing line.
木星与土星引发的引力错乱
The gravitational chaos of Jupiter and Saturn
使得小星体不断撞击类地行星及其卫星
is battering the inner Solar System's planets and moons
现在我们称其为"后期重轰炸期"
in an event now known as the late heavy bombardment.
许多外太阳系的星体
A lot of the material in the outter Solar System,
这些彗星都飞入内太阳系
these comets fell into the inner Solar System
并与类地行星及其卫星发生碰撞
where they collided with the inner planets and the moon,
我们今天见到的陨石坑就是这样形成的
creating the craters that we see today.
一些研究人员认为
Some researchers believe
频繁的撞击使地球一次又一次地生灵涂炭
collisions may have repeatedly sterilized the Earth,
如果有生命产生 则因此毁灭
and that if life had formed, it was wiped out...
而不得不又从零开始
And had to start anew.
但这从天而降 砸向地球的星体
But the impact of objects from space,
以及随之而来的一番天崩地裂
along with their violence,
也可能为地球带来福祉
may have also brought a benefit.
地球若非被那些来自外太阳系的星体
The Earth might not have all the water it does today
狂轰滥炸一番
had it not been bombarded by
今天的地球上就不会有这么多的水
material from the outer Solar System.
一些科学家推测
Some have speculated
今天我们地球上的很多水
that much of the water we have on Earth
其实都是"后期重轰炸期"时
is actually a result of impacts
对地球狂轰滥炸的那些星体带来的
from the late heavy bombardment period.
在距离太阳系的诞生46亿年的今天
Today, 4.6 billion years after the Solar System's birth,
但巨型星子撞击地球的隐患依然存在
the ongoing if remote danger of a massive asteroid strike
而这意味着 我们尚不能高枕无忧
means the story is not over.
我们更应该关注的是
More important, though,
那上百颗坠落在地球上
are the hundreds of tiny asteroids
成为陨石的微型星子
hitting the planet as meteorites.
通过对这些陨石的分析研究
Studying them tells us
我们便可以了解到太阳系的形成过程
if the making of the Solar System
是否正如我们想象的那样
really happened when and how we think it did.
这块石头是从艾伦德陨星采下的样本
I'm holding a sample of the Allende meteorite.
艾伦德陨星是一块于1969年陨落在
The Allende meteorite is a fragment of rock
墨西哥艾伦德村附近的岩石
that fell in Mexico near the village of Allende in 1969.
这块陨石的组成部分包括了
One of the components of the meteorite
这些富含钙元素与铝元素的杂质
are these calcium-aluminum-rich inclusions,
就是这些在其表面的白色物质
these white objects that you can see on the surface.
我们通过放射性同位素测试得知
These are the oldest known materials in the Solar System,
它们是太阳系中已知的最古老物质
and we know this by age dating with radiogenic isotopes.
在加州大学洛杉矶分校的高科技试验室里
In his high-tech lab at UCLA,
天体化学家艾德·杨和他的同事们
cosmochemist Ed Young and his colleagues
在对古老陨石的小样本进行仔细的化验
carefully examine tiny samples of ancient meteorites.
样本中部有一块很大的白色杂质
There's a big white fragment in the middle
我们需要把它切割出来
which we want to cut out.
用试验室中精密的激光仪器对准这块杂质
The lab's precision lasers aim at the fragments,
在陨石上烧灼出一个个头发那么细的小孔
blasting out holes no wider than a human hair.
研究人员仔细地分析测量其中的放射性元素
Sophisticated analysis measures radioactive elements,
这些放射性元素可以告诉我们其年代
which serve as atomic clocks.
2011年初 在亚利桑那州立大学
In early 2011, cosmochemists in a similar lab
一个类似的试验室 那里的天体化学家
at Arizona State University
精确地测定出一块在北非发现的陨石
dated part of a north African meteorite
产自四十亿六千八百二十万年前
to an incredibly accurate 4.5682 billion years old,
迄今已来是在地球上发现的最古老的物质
the oldest material ever found on earth,
甚至比地球自己的年龄还要大
older than the planet itself.
2011年8月
In August 2011,
"黎明号"探测器到达了
the Dawn spacecraft arrived
星子带 大多数陨石都来自于此
in the asteroid belt, source of most meteorites.
探测器接近了第二大星子 灶神星
Close-up pictures of Vesta,
并拍下了特写镜头
the second largest asteroid,
从此 人们对太阳系诞生史的研究
open a new epoch
翻开了新的一页
in telling the Solar System's story.
"黎明号"执行的任务十分令人兴奋
One of the exciting things about the Dawn Mission
因为这是我们第一次得以目睹
is that we're gonna get our first glimpse into something
这个恰恰与太阳系
that was essentially a mini-planet that was formed
同时诞生的星子
right at the beginning of the Solar System.
自其于太阳系初期诞生以来
Since its birth early in the Solar System's history,
灶神星就没怎么经历过风吹雨打
Vesta has been undisturbed by weather
也未受到什么地质作用力的影响
or many of the geologic forces
不像其他行星饱受风雨和地壳运动的摧残
that have changed the planets over time.
与其他的大行星一样 灶神星也有火山
Just like some of the larger planets, it has volcanoes.
它也有内核
It has a core.
但与其他的大行星不同的是
But unlike these larger planets,
在过去的四十五亿年中
not much else has happened to it
它的表面并没怎么受到其他外力的影响
in the past four and half billion years.
借助对灶神星勘测
So we essentially get a window back into
我们得以研究太阳系刚刚诞生时的情况
that very earliest history of the Solar System.
"黎明号"将围绕灶神星运转一年
Dawn will orbit Vesta for a year
随后它将前往最大的星子 谷神星
before going on to spend another year
并围绕它运转一年的时间
orbiting the largest asteroid, Ceres.
与此同时 航空航天局的"朱诺"探测器
Meanwhile, NASA's Juno probe
也将开始其前往木星的旅程
has just begun its voyage to Jupiter,
它造访这颗巨行星的任务是
where it will visit the giant planet
探测出它到底有没有固态的内核
to determine if it really does have a solid core
如果有 那个内核是否像科学家想象的
and formed early and quickly,
是在木星诞生初期迅速形成的
as scientists now believe.
而更加值得我们留意的
Even more crucial are other stars
是那些同样拥有自己太阳系的恒星
with their own solar systems,
其形成过程有助于我们了解自己的太阳系
whose formation sheds essential light on our own.
我们之所以要了解太阳系的形成过程
The most important reason for understanding
其中最重要的原因就是
how the Solar System was made
我们想知道太阳系的存在是否寻常
was to find out whether or not we're normal.
当你用人们现在造出的天文望远镜
When you look out and look at other solar systems
向太空眺望 寻找其他太阳系
being made with our telescopes today,
比如但你放眼猎户座星云或是其他地方
for example in Orion and other places,
你的心中可能会有这样的疑问
we want to answer the question,
"太阳系的存在究竟有多普遍"
"How normal is this solar system?"
于2009年开始执行的开普勒任务
Launched in 2009, the Kepler mission
现在正如火如荼地进行着
is now running full-blast
到目前为止 它已甄别出了
and has identified
1200个可能围绕其他恒星公转的行星
1,200 possible planets around other stars.
一些行星系统中会出现木星那么大的行星
Some systems have Jupiter-sized planets
它们靠近系中的恒星运转或是偏向运转
close to their suns or in lopsided orbits.
还有一些行星系统中只有小号的行星
Others have only small planets
它们紧密聚集在那颗恒星能照射到的地方
crowded closely in the hot zone of their stars.
然而 我们的太阳系却与众不同
Our Solar System, however,
太阳系中的行星轨道都接近圆形
has its planets in near-circular orbits,
一环一环稳定地排列着
spread out in a stable arrangement
这看上去简直是过于完美了
that seems almost too perfect.
在过去十年中 当我们不断发现那些
One of the great surprises of the last decade
太阳系外行星系统时 最令人吃惊的是
as we started to discover other planetary systems
我们的太阳系似乎是个怪胎
was the fact that our Solar system seems to be one of the odd balls.
这主要是因为太阳系太规律了
Mostly because our own Solar System is so regular.
太阳系的形成过程是否与
Is the Solar System made by processes
今日其他行星系统形成相同
that we can observe going on today,
又或者 我们的太阳是独一无二的
or are we somehow special?
这又引出了另一个问题
This goes to the point of
即地球上的生命是否是独一无二的
whether or not life is special.
这恐怕是所有问题中
And that question is perhaps
最重要的一个了
the most important one of all
因为对太阳及其行星的生命历程的探寻
as the life story of the sun and its planets
归根结底是探寻生命本身的历程
essentially becomes the lifestory of life itself.
地球上的人类以及地球本身
Humanity on Earth, and our ultimate place.
在茫茫宇宙中 是否只此一例
Alone or among many in the universe.